was there ever something that held us
all together as americans that was as
as binding of an experience as it is to
be french or to be
chinese or to be anybody else
um i think so maybe i'm going to have to
answer this question
yes or no yes and no because you want to
say as much
right well maybe not as much because if
you're chinese you know
that chinese civilization is literally 5
000 years old right
and your ancestors on that soil you may
not know the names back
more than two three generations go back
millennia right and you're part of a
culture that's gone through
all kinds of now you know china really
only becomes china about 2 000 years ago
as we know it but that's still
long 2 000 years is a long time
you know english the english have very
clear records of
monarchs and aristocracies and
parliamentary debates
and bill's been laws being passed going
back
um you know almost a millennium too
or if not more than a millennium but you
know the magna carta is 12 15
for god's sake so not i don't think the
united states can be
can have a national identity that's as
deep-rooted as
some of these other countries right but
did it have something like that that we
deliberately fractured
and by the way these some of these other
i mean the chinese are in better shape
than we are because as evil as their
leadership is in many ways they're not
dumb enough to deliberately
uh fracture the national identity of the
population whereas things aren't great
right now in the national cultures of
england or france i'd say england is
britain is worse off than france by by
some significant degree
but france has got its own problems and
i say that not to bash france
i love france but we did put together
this is chapter two is all about this
and it's the chapter that i think i've
gotten the most criticism for
not because people well i've gotten two
criticisms for it one is people said
boring it reads like a master's thesis
or something and like
academic who cares um and then from the
right i get oh that's
anton trying to keep civic nationalism
alive when he should know by now that
it's totally dead
and there's no hope for it and i want to
say is first of all
is the problem that is the ditch that
we're in right now owing to civic
nationalism
and in part i answer that the founders
didn't have a choice they had to adopt
civic nationalism
right because the facts on the ground in
1776 as we form
the social compact with the declaration
of independence is the country is
already a multi-ethnic
society now it's not as multi-ethnic as
it is now but it wasn't like we could
just say
hey this is this is you know new england
and we're all english well
we got all these other it was already
pluralistically religious it was it had
a lot of
regional ethnic religious and other
differences
and it had to see englishness and
frenchness and chineseness and
japaneseness
come together over centuries and
millennia and nobody knows how
it happened historians spend all their
time you know reading as many old books
as they can archaeologists go around and
digging and finding the roots of this
and then find you know well
wow look at this building that dates
from 75 years before the earliest
dwelling we had ever found here before
right and they're trying to piece it
together
but in the case of all of those nations
nobody sits down
one you know in an assembly in
philadelphia or wherever one day and
says
we are splitting off from you and we are
becoming us
sign here right explicitly forms the
social compact all of a sudden we are as
first paragraph of the declaration of
independence says we are then one people
how do we bind those people together
well that's one of the ways that they
did it and it's not the only way
uh john jay says in federalists too
um how lucky we are
to be so alike in our habits and
sentiments
right to uh to cherish the same
principles of government to have similar
ways of life to have a similar type of
religion
to have a common language right um and
we just fought the revolutionary war
nothing brings people together in a way
like struggle does you
it's the same story you hear about these
guys who haven't seen each other they
see each other once a year for 50 years
but like nine months
in a combat situation somewhere bombs
them for life so the revolutionary war
did that
for the american people so i get
these critics to my right who say
um american amer the idea of what it
means to be an american has become
so ridiculously abstract that you know
we just basically say everybody in the
in the world is a potential american and
so all you know we can we can invite
you know as many tens of millions of
people as we want and america is an idea
and all you have to do is accept the
idea and you're american and there's
nothing to america
and they say that's total hogwash and i
agree with them that is total hogwash
but they i wish my critics would be more
willing
to concede the fact that
um america the
the american way of doing it has worked
in the sense that like
when i'm just take my own ancestors
right
of my eight great grandparents six are
italian one was greek and one was
lebanese
all of whom got here in a period between
about 1880 and 1910
initially
neither myself nor any of my relatives
uh nor my children
i feel we're sick we're totally american
you know just completely totally
americanized welcomed into the social
compact
completely assimilated into the culture
in every way and like
that shows the success what america can
do when these processes are working and
i can i can point to a lot of different
people
um one of my teachers one of harry
jaffa's best students uh he
his father his parents got him out of
hungary in 1956 as the russians rolled
in
when he was 10 years old and he grew up
in hollywood you know
went to hollywood i the literal
hollywood high on hollywood on
not yet i can't i think it's on sunset
boulevard anyway
uh where lana turner went you know and
was discovered at the soda fountain by a
talent scout and this stuff
peter schramm was his name he died a few
years ago right sram
born in hungary 10 years in hungary
learned perfect english learned amer
completely americanized by america
completely
his his old quip used to be that he was
born american but in the wrong place
right so if if i'm willing more than
willing because i think it's right and i
attack
those notions of america as an
abstraction i attack it pretty
vigorously in the book to say
yeah america is not just an idea there's
more to it than that but i wish the
people to my right who criticized me
would admit
uh america has been successful at doing
exactly
the thing that they say can't be done
there was no way in 1770 like if if
the only way for nationhood to be real
is a
century's rooted ethnic identity then
you have to say the american revolution
was completely unjust and shouldn't have
happened and there should never have
been in america
now that's the left-wing position today
there should never have been in america
because america is fundamentally evil
if the right is going to be on the same
spot as the left on the question of the
existence and the justice of the
existence of america
then i gotta step back and say goodbye
to both of them
so one time you say there's not an
american
consciousness that binds us together
anymore
because the left has spent 50 years
hammering away at it and fracturing it
yeah just smashing it right as exactly
as what arthur
schlesinger warned about they were there
was about halfway into the process when
he wrote that book
and now the process has been completed
except that i still say
there's i don't know what it is there's
40 there's 50 percent maybe 60
of the population whatever it is i say
in the book somewhere that
you know it's in chapter two i do i say
you know the people that i'm speaking to
are people who identify
as american and only as american and
those people
exist by the tens of millions in this
country the problem is
that there are tens of millions who feel
the exact opposite and they control
all the commanding heights of discourse
power money
and so on i'm a little confused and and
i pardoned me for being
elementary on this no
amount of propaganda or politicizing
will change
the ethnic nature of being chinese
and china propaganda and ideas and
discourse and whatever you're saying
is chipping away and destroying what it
is to be
american so by that of my understanding
that this american consciousness is
a concept not a blood a
language a history but really
an idea i know i think it's i think it's
both
right so let's say let's say one of the
outcomes that i outlined in chapter
seven comes to pass
right the left gets back into total
power
push the pedal to the floor crash the
system
and the american system ceases to
function
at some point in the in the future right
there will still be people alive on the
north american continent
granted unless there's you know a real
pandemic that kills everybody or a
nuclear war or something people are
going to be alive here they're not going
to have a government they're going to
self-organize
they're going to start they're going to
do exactly what aristotle says people do
the in the politics he says people do
which is they come together
to do jointly what cannot be done or
cannot be done well
alone right they're gonna do that now
i don't know about you if you let's just
pick any part of the country you want
montana idaho wisconsin michigan
tennessee
arkansas the texas panhandle the
oklahoma panhandle and you get a bunch
of people together
are they all going to suddenly say you
know well i'm actually not american
i'm italian so i'm gonna found in like a
little italian republic here and i'll
just get all the italians together by
the way do any of you speak italian
well you know you know my nona did but
she's been dead since
you know 1965. i can boil spaghetti
though
you know if everybody tries to break
down their own ethnic say i'm going to
revert to my true roots
i don't think my sense is there there
are probably some people in america who
feel that way that like i'm truly this
but i know i live here
but i think most people feel like no i'm
truly american and then the other
problem is
you know how many of us are any of our
are a majority
one ethnicity or the other i mean i'm
three quarters italian which is actually
for a lot of people i know you know you
know um
more dominated by one particular
ethnicity than a lot of people i was
like
well i'm french and i'm english and you
know maybe i have a little cherokee
indian if you're elizabeth warren you
know
like they can name six seven different
things and none of them is a majority so
what are you
in that case so in addition to uh that i
don't
think in my experience this is not the
way americans think in their own heart
but i also think it's just gonna be
completely impractical what do we and
then what are we gonna do
so the the wokarati break the united
states of america and
no the people still alive on the north
american continent must reorganize
themselves
i mean are we gonna like try to carve
out little well this is for the italians
but what if you're half italian and what
if you're like
you know and then this one's for the
greeks and this one's for the what
how how's that gonna work and then you
know but that's before you even get into
the question of other ethnicities i
don't think people have really
quite thought this through i think their
their hatred civic nationalism for
certain
quarters of the right has just become a
hate term a kind of a swear term
and so rather than trying to think
through practical reality on this
um they just try to find people who they
say adhere to it and therefore those
were the bad guys and that's really why
i wrote
the boring and pedant oh my god my
publisher's going to shoot me
the allegedly boring and pedantic
chapter 2 because i think all this stuff
has to be thought through
and i'd rather provoke a bunch of people
to write back at me that i was wrong it
was terrible but it forced them to start
thinking about it
then just leave these questions out
lying there i have been involved in
politics
more intensely than my life in the last
five years i wrote a book called
democrat to deplorable i was a lifelong
obama or a lifelong democrat voter
obama voter around 2014 2015 i saw
all these writings on the wall i
supported trump
i wrote a book all about it why and i
see so many echoes
for mine is more of like on the ground
the stories of people who had the same
transformative experience and then yours
is sort of coming at it from a
historical and a high level view
but one of the things that i
consistently struggled with
i'm half irish half ashkenazi my family
came here late 19th early 20th century
i feel 100 american um
i hear the magic dirt arguments or
counter arguments i hear people's
trashing
civic nationalism back in 2016 we had
you know
more unsavory people in the coalition
stressing ethno divisions and whatnot
and and i still haven't
zeroed down and been able to succinctly
say
what is this american consciousness that
that we
that that is uniquely american and is it
an
idea or is it a heritage or is it a
history or is it language
and so for me that chapter was really
pertinent and fantastic and i think it's
a key
argument in sort of forming this
anti-globalist
neoliberal neoconservative identity
right so you know the iconoclasm of 2020
where we're going to rename everything
and tear down statues and you know we're
gonna
kind of do what um you know what is an
iconoclast he's somebody who goes into
churches and he
busts up the art because it's uh uh in
his
religious uh puritanical view offensive
to god
that beautiful you know it offends the
commander against braven images
that's the idea um okay
i have i have no no strand of dna in me
that's present in north america before
uh 1888 not and yet i revere george
washington as if he's the father of my
country
now to a strict ethno-nationalist he
would say that i suffer from false
consciousness or something
right oh you can't claim that but you i
can claim garibaldi
even though i wasn't born in italy i
didn't grow up speaking italian i had to
teach myself to read italian so that i
could learn machiavelli
and i love visiting italy it's great
it's fun i like the food
architecture but i don't feel at home
there i don't feel italian there
now if you know my life went sideways in
some way and i had to flee
right but you only there were places you
could end up um
uh you know i like i like the food i
like the tailoring
there's a lot of things like the wine
there's a lot of things i like about it
but
like that that kind of persistent
and the other the other point too that i
would make so again
i i feel only loyal to america i feel
only loyal
to americans i am inspired by american
heroes and
and heritage and the past as if it's my
history
i guess yes there's something um
irrational about that in a certain way
but i'd have to say why like
just because somebody was born in italy
um
you know that
legitimize being say proud of
michelangelo
where i was born in america but i can't
be proud of george washington because my
dna doesn't trace
to 1776 there but if my dna traced to
yeah
it's it's a kind of weird argument that
i i don't get that i don't think adds up
i don't think i'm stating this
precisely but what they want to say is
well you're you're in you're an alien
well
i guess then everybody's in it i mean
they're
if you go in that direction you're
feeding into the left wing line of
thought which is that america is
illegitimate right so if we all have to
be ethno-nationalists
well then um what's so magical about
getting you know
getting on a boat from you're coming to
america but those people are okay
because there were the american well why
did you leave it why aren't you english
right well i'm i'm mayflower stock so i
can be american but you can't because
you your ancestors came later
right well why you then that means
you're english you should be loyal to
that not to this
there only is america because a bunch of
people came here and made
america okay and we the reason why this
confuses people
is because you know we saw it happen
in in in in the modern age when
there were much more complete records
and so on i could ask the same question
about so what makes a
when does an english person become an
english person right there's britons on
the british isle
then the romans come then they
intermarry are we are we english yet
why does it why are why are the
anglo-saxons called anglo-saxons
saxony is in germany it's because a
bunch of people from northern europe
come over and struggle
are they english then you get the norman
conquest in 1066.
are we have we gotten there yet now from
that point on
until the mass migrations following
world war ii the english population was
very very stable
it's basically the same there was no
almost zero net immigration
and you know a little bit here and there
but very very very stable
the but englishness somehow is banged
together
over the course of a thousand years
um without an obvious migratory movement
that you get
from northern europe to the united you
know to the north american continent
found in the united states and of course
without a signing ceremony
this is what confuses people so they
think like um
well that's the natural way to do it
well if that's the natural way to do it
and the only way to do it in this way is
illegitimate then you've sort of bought
the left-wing argument that no
that there shouldn't be an american no
one from europe should ever come to
america
right if if your ethnic status is the
thing
then then both the puritans and the
cavaliers they're
they're just english and they should
never have left right and the other
thing that bothers me that i find
inconsistent about this argument is
people say no no
um the tradition is the only thing we
have to get back to tradition
all right fair enough i'm not against
tradition i'm actually pro tradition in
a lot of ways if it's a good tradition
but then that gets you into the whole
philosophical question of how do you
evaluate tradition you have to have a
philosophical framework right
plato and aristotle would say because
there's an idea of the good and i can
evaluate anything in the light of that
just because it's old doesn't mean it's
good necessarily but all right
or bad or bad yeah right
um uh well we have to get back to
tradition
okay well the american tradition is
fighting the revolution
the american tradition is the
declaration of independence the american
tradition is the constitution and the
northwest ordinance and the bill of
rights
and all of these things so in the name
of tradition are we supposed to reject
our tradition
we're americans we're for tradition but
my god we really do hate the revolution
which gave birth to this country
and we really do hate the fundamental
charters of our liberties which are too
abstract and enlightenment
you know we're supposed to so what
tradition are we supposed to go back to
some medieval tradition
i'm very sympathetic to this argument
they have not sorted this out and i'm
sure there's a lot of people listening
right now
who are saying you know
can i use like a semi-bad language on
this podcast
yeah dude go ahead he's a [ __ ] right and
he's a sibnet
we knew it all along i like you know
have at it but rather than
i would i would ask people who want to
make that argument
buy the book i could use the money but
leave that aside read
chapter 2 with care and see if you can
give me an actual
point by point reputation of it because
i'd love to read